With our wire frames in hand, we're ready
to block out the basic structure of our
website.
Over the last few years, new HTML elements
have become available along with several
new technologies.
Collectively, these new elements and
technologies are referred to as HTML5.
Now, this might imply a new version of
HTML.
But it's a little bit of a misnomer.
I'm just telling you this now so that
when you hear other web designers and
developers
use the term HTML5, you don't get
confused.
All it really means are some new HTML
elements that weren't
available previously, along with a few new
pieces of browser technology.
Now, let's get coding.
First, let's get rid of these style tags.
I'm going to highlight this entire area
and press
the Delete key.
We don't need them because we'll add style
later on.
We'll hold on to our headline, because we
will still need it later.
Every web page has to start with what's
called a document type, or doc type for
short.
And it looks like this.
Start out with an opening angle bracket,
an exclamation point.
The word doc type
in all capital letters, a space, the word
html
in lower case letters, and then a closing
angle bracket.
There's no closing tag and this tag also
won't create anything that's visible on
the page.
There are many other tags like this that
only serve structural purposes and
are not actually visible to the site
visitor.
This doc type basically tells the browser
that this is
an HTML document and that's how it should
be interpreted.
The doc type should always be the first
thing on the page.
And it should always be at the top,
without any space before it.
Now, let's create an HTML element.
Of course, everything that we'll be
creating here is an HTML element.
But this element is actually called HTML.
[SOUND].
This will serve as the root of our
document structure, and
similar to the doc type, it won't be
visible to visitors.
I'm going to wrap our headline with the
HTML tags and
then indent it, so that I can easily see
that it's nested.
To do this, I'm going to highlight our h1
element.
I'm going to cut it by hitting Cmd+X on a
Mac or Ctrl+X on Windows.
Then I'm going to click inside of our HTML
element,
create some space, then I'm going to paste
it by hitting Cmd+V on
a Mac or Ctrl+V on Windows.
Then I'm going
to go to the beginning of the line and hit
Tab to indent it.
One way you can go quickly from the
beginning to the end of
the line, or vice versa, is by holding
down the Command key and using
the arrows, if you're on a mac, or
hitting Control and the arrows if you're
on Windows.
So for example, on my Mac here, I can hit
Command
and right arrow to go to the end of the
line.
Or Command and left arrow to go to the
beginning of the line.
This handy tip will help you navigate text
more quickly.
Now we're ready to add two more elements
to our page,
which are the head element and the body
element.
Both of these need to go inside of our
HTML element.
I'm going to type head and I'm just going
to leave that right above our h1.
Gonna go to the end of the line and create
a
new line and then I'm going to type a body
element.
Once again our h1 element needs to go
inside of the body.
And in this case, I'm going to use a new
keyboard shortcut to
actually highlight this body element.
To do this on a Mac, you can hit Cmd+Shift
and then the arrow key depending on the
direction that you want to highlight.
To do this on Windows, you just hit
Ctrl+Shift and then the direction you want
to highlight.
So on my Mac, with my insertion point in
between the two tags,
I'm going to Cmd+Shift and then right
arrow to
highlight it, Cmd+X to cut it I'm gonna go
to the
end of the line here, and paste in that
body tag.
And then I'm going to indent this line
just
like that.
That way I'll know my h1 is nested
inside of my body.
Which is also nested inside of my HTML.
At this point, you're probably starting to
see why indentation is so important.
When you have a much larger HTML file, as
we will later on, it's important to
use indentation so that you can see how
elements are nested inside of one another.
Now let's talk about these two elements
that we
just added.
The head element will contain what's
called meta information, about
our document, which again won't be visible
to site visitors.
However, it will contain important
information like
CSS, which will modify the visuals later
on.
The head element is not the same thing as
the website header we wire framed earlier.
I know that's a little bit confusing right
now but don't worry, we'll explain the
difference soon.
The body element, which we typed right
here
will contain the rest of our website
content.
In other words, this is the body of the
document.
Once again, I've indented my headline
element further
because it's two levels deep here inside
of
HTML and body.
Now, let's jump inside of the head
and hit Enter, to create some space.
Hit Tab to indent our code.
And then, let's type a title for our
website.
I'm going to write my name,
followed by a space and a vertical pipe
which
you can type by hitting Shift and the
backslash key.
Then another space, and I'm going to type
the word designer.
Because this website is going to be my
design portfolio.
You might wanna put something else, like
photographer or expert
cupcake baker.
The title tag usually appears in browser
tabs so you know what website you're
visiting.
It will also appear in search engine
result pages.
Now let's add the character set for the
page just above the title.
That will look like this.
We'll type the word meta followed
by charset, an equals sign and
then two double quotes.
Inside of the double quotes, we're
going to type utf- and the number
eight.
And finally, we need to close our Meta
tag, this code looks a little bit
intimidating, but don't let it scare you.
It's simply telling the browser how our
webpage
is formatted and what types of characters
are used.
Similar to the DOC type, it's not visible
to the site visitor.
It also doesn't have a closing tag.
Inside of this meta tag, you'll notice
we've used some new syntax.
We have a word followed by an equals sign,
which is then followed by a value wrapped
in double quotes.
This is called an attribute.
Attributes are extra information inside of
an HTML tag
that provides key information to the
browser about how the page is built.
We'll learn more about how to use
attributes on
many other elements, but for now, let's
focus on what
this attribute means.
The literal translation here is that the
character set or charset should be utf-8,
or universal character set transformation
format, eight bit.
Don't worry about memorizing that.
In fact, I even had to look it up
and I've been making websites for more
than a decade.
Again, it just describes how our page is
formatted.