Now, let's dig into the body element, and
add some real page
structure.
I'm going to jump
into the body, and type a header tag, and
then I'm going to put our h1 inside of the
header.
Just below the header, I'm going
to create a section element.
And then below that, I'm going to create a
footer.
One thing you'll notice about WorkSpaces
is, is that if you type enough of
the element that you're trying to create
it will auto complete it for you.
If I type some of the element here
and then hit enter it will automatically
complete
the rest of the element name.
If I then close the tag, it
will add the closing tag for me.
Again, this is just more
code completion that allows you to type
faster by typing less.
Now, I've added three new elements here,
the header
element, the section element and the
footer element.
This provides the basic structure for our
site content,
let's go through each one of these new
elements.
The header element is different than the
head element that we added earlier.
The head element is just for the web
browser to read meta data about the
HTML document.
This new header element is
actually a part of the site's content and
helps
structure the information that we're
displaying to site visitors.
Inside of it we have the first level
headline that
we created earlier and I've made sure to
continue indenting properly.
Now, before we move on to the section and
footer, let's
add a second level headline that matches
the title we created earlier.
The headline will be slightly smaller than
our
first level headline when it's rendered on
our webpage.
So, after my first level headline, I'm
going to type h2.
And then, inside of that, I'm going to
type, designer.
Now, this section element will soon
contain our image gallery.
Sections, just as the name implies, break
up a page
into logical groupings of information,
just like sections of a newspaper.
We're not ready to build our gallery just
yet but let's add a temporary
placeholder paragraph, so that when we
preview
the page, we'll know where this section
appears.
So, inside of my section,
I'm going to type a paragraph element
and I'm going to say, gallery will go
here.
The footer element is a complement to the
header element.
Here we can put things like copyright
information
or social media links, similar to the
header,
this is a good place to put information
that we want to feature on every page.
Unlike the header, this information isn't
really important enough to put at the
top of the page, so we're de-emphasizing
it by putting it at the bottom.
Let's add a paragraph that contains
copyright information.
So, inside of my footer here,
I'm going to create a new paragraph and
you'll notice that when I hit enter to
open up a tag, WorkSpaces automatically
indents for
me, I didn't have to type tab there.
Now, let's create our paragraph, so I'm
going
to type a paragraph element or P tag
there.
And, we're going to use some special code
here,
and I'm gonna type it out, then explain
it.
So, I'm going to type an ampersand, so
I'll hit
Shift and then the number seven on my
keyboard for ampersand.
Then, I'm going to type the word, copy.
Followed by a semicolon.
And you can see in the code completion
there that WorkSpaces provides, what that
might do.
So, we'll talk about that in a minute.
Then after my semicolon there, I'm going
to type a space.
I'm going to type 2014, and I'm going to
type Nick Pettit followed by a period.
This special syntax that we typed is
a character that doesn't appear on our
keyboard.
In fact, it is the copyright character.
So, we need to type what's called
an HTML entity to make it appear.
There are lots
of HTML entities like this, but there's no
need to memorize them.
Most web designers and developers just go
to a
search engine when they need to look them
up.
In the notes for this video, you'll find a
link that
lists them out for you.
The syntax follows the pattern of an
ampersand followed by the name of the
symbol and then a semi colon.
So, you can go ahead and type an ampersand
here in WorkSpaces
will automatically generate a list of HTML
entities for you to choose from.
As you can see there are quite a lot of
them but if you
go ahead and continue typing it will
narrow down the list as you type.
But we don't need a second special
character there,
so I'm just going to go ahead and delete
that.
Now, let's save our webpage and we're
going to preview it.
However, before we open the preview
window, I want you to try and visualize
what you think the page will look like.
Now, let's open it up.
Does the page look like what you were
expecting?
Right now, it's pretty underwhelming.
It's just a white background and some
black text.
And only the most basic default styling
that's been applied automatically by the
browser.
We're going to add lots more life to this
page
with CSS, but first, we need to finish up
the content.
One thing I would like you to notice
right now though, is the sequence of the
content.
From the top down to the bottom, our page
has a header with
our name, followed by a second level
headline that we've made.
Then this section with the content inside
which right now is just a temporary
paragraph.
Followed by the
footer down at the bottom.
This is exactly the same order that our
elements appear in our code.
In other words, we can't just put things
into our HTML randomly.
It should appear in the order that we
would like it to appear on the page.
Starting from the top left corner and
working our way down the page.
We just covered a lot of new HTML
elements, including the doc type, the HTML
element, meta element, title element, head
and body
elements, and the header section and
footer elements.
Before we continue, let's take a quick
code challenge
to make sure that you've mastered this
important information.