So far we've just been working with code,
but before we
move any further we should explore the
design of our website.
Just to serve as a reminder, this is what
our project will look like when it's done.
When you're creating projects on your own
the design won't
be done for you like it is in this case.
So it's important that we walk through
some
of the design decisions here and
understand them.
The design process from one site to
another
will always vary, but for our purposes we
can break things down like this.
First, we're going to decide on goals,
then we'll list out
the page elements, and finally we'll
layout the pages with shapes.
I'm going to work through the design on
paper, and I strongly encourage you to
follow along.
First, we should decide on an overall goal
for our site.
In these lessons,
this website will a design portfolio with
a goal of booking new work.
However, there will be many opportunities
along the way
for you to customize this website for your
own needs.
For example, your site's goal might be to
showcase your arts and crafts, or perhaps
you want to create a gallery of photos to
share with your family and friends.
Once you've decided on your own goal we
should list out the page
elements we'll need.
For this website we'll need an image
gallery, an about page, and a contact
page.
We'll also need a simple header with a
title and navigation.
Often this site-wide header is called top
level navigation.
We'll also need a site footer.
This image gallery will showcase our work.
The about page will provide some context
for the
website as a whole and tell the visitor
more information.
And then the contact page will give the
visitor a way to get in touch.
This is especially important for a design
portfolio where we're trying to get new
work.
With our list in hand, let's quickly lay
out our three page website.
We're going to use a technique called wire
framing to
lay out the shapes and visual structure of
our site.
This is a much faster way to experiment
with site layout before you spend lots of
time writing code.
We're also going to design the mobile
version of the
site and then work our way up to more
complex layouts.
I'm going to layout our gallery as a grid
with two images in each row.
Underneath each image will be a short
caption that gives the image some context.
This layout
will allow us enough room to make the
images large so they command a lot of
attention.
Now, let's layout the contact page and
about page.
Both of these pages are pretty simple, so
they can follow the same basic layout.
We'll create a single column and stack
everything, because mobile
sites don't really have enough room for
too many columns.
But they're great at scrolling.
In the case of our about page,
we'll add a photo and a paragraph about
ourselves.
For the contact page, we'll write a
paragraph describing how best to reach us,
along with details like an email address,
phone number and Twitter account.
That's about it for the mobile site.
Now let's take these same pages and make
them work for tablets and desktops.
We have a lot more width to work with
here,
so I'm going to spread apart the logo text
and the navigation in the header.
Then on the gallery page, I'm going to
break up my two columns into three
columns.
Finally, on our about page and contact
page, I'm going to create two
columns and give our page elements a
little bit more room to breathe.
Looks good.
Our quick wire frames
are pretty much done.
If we were building a more complex website
we might wanna take things
further and build high fidelity mock ups
in an image editing tool like Photoshop.
However, this is a simple website.
And as we build it in HTML and CSS we can
fill in the details along the way.