Now let's continue.
I'm going to set the font weight to
normal.
so font weight is going to be normal.
So this will basically unbold our headline
because headline elements are bold by
default.
And then I'm going to set the line-height
to 0.8 ems.
Now the line-height
property determines the amount of space
between each line of text.
This is more important in paragraph text,
and actually it's more apparent in
paragraph text.
But we want to adjust the spacing here as
well.
Again we're using relative ems as the unit
here.
Now let's style or second level headline,
and I'm going to type out the code and
then explain it after I'm done typing.
So font size is going to be 0.75 ems.
The margin is going to be negative 5
pixels,
0 and then 0; so we're using 3 values
there.
And then the font weight is going to be
normal.
So what is all this mean?
Well the font size and font weight should
be
familiar to you The font weight being set
to normal
will basically unbold our text like we
just did previously,
and I'll see what that looks like in a
moment.
And then the font size is set to 0.75 ms,
so that will
make the font size actually pretty small,
because remember, this is a multiplier.
But the new thing I've done here is
set a negative margin, and I've also set
three
values for the margin instead of two like
we've been using previously.
The first value here, sets the top.
The second
value, sets the left and right.
And the third value sets the bottom.
In other words, this element only has
margins applied to
the top.
This negative value that we're applying to
the top will actually pull the
element closer to the other elements
around it, rather than pushing it away.
This is a common technique when you want
elements
to be tighter together, especially when
you're styling typography.
We're going to do more styling throughout,
but
let's finish up some more font related
stuff.
So
I'm going to save that out, and up here.
I'm going to select the body element once
again.
So let's come up to the top here, and
select our body again.
And we've already selected our body down
in our colors,
but I want this to be separate from our
colors.
And easy to read.
So, we're going to create a second body
selector here.
And we're gonna apply the other font we
picked out, which is open Sans.
And we're going to fall back to Sans
Serif, if for some reason Open Sans isn't
available.
This will set everything
on the site to use Open Sans because we're
applying it to the body.
With the exception of our first-level
headline,
which has another font applied to it and
is more specific than the body, so it will
be over-ridden for that one element.
This is a good example of how cascading in
CSS works.
To wrap this up, we're going to style the
navigation section and the footer.
We're not going to use any new properties
or techniques.
Instead, I want you to try and follow
along, and understand what we're doing.
So, let's go ahead and create a
new section here by copying our multi-line
comment.
And let's scroll down here.
And I'm gonna put a new multi-line comment
just after our
h2 there.
And I'm going to call those, navigation.
And then I'm going to select our nav
element here.
And we already have a selector for this,
but again, not selecting colors.
And I wanna keep that separate in this
particular project.
But you could put them together if you'd
like.
I'm going to align the text center in our
nav.
I'm going to set some padding on the top
and
bottom to ten pixels, and zero on the left
and right.
And then I'm going to apply
some margin to the top, but I want
everything else to be zero for our
navigation.
Now I'm going to select this multi-line
comment once again, and
just after our navigation here, I'm going
to create a new one for the footer.
And I'm going to select our footer,
and then we're going to create some
decorations
inside of our rule here.
So we're going to set the font size to
0.75 ms.
So the font in our footer will be
relatively small.
We're gonna set the text alignment to be
center, once again.
We're going to set the padding on the top
to
50 pixels, so we are actually using a new
property here.
Padding, top.
Which is just another way of
specifying that we only want padding on
the top, and then finally,
we're going to set the color to this very
light grey color here.
So, let's go ahead and save this and
refresh the page to see how this looks.
If I resize the browser window here, it
will
cut off our images and we'll fix that
later on.
But you can start to see our mobile
website coming together.
We have our footer here.
Ad we have the header up at the top.
There still some spacing issues here, and
a lot of alignment issues, and like I said
the images are still entirely too large.
There's a few problems here, but we're
going to fix all of those things.
The more you practice with fonts and
typography properties in CSS, the better
you'll get.
It's important that you play with these as
much as you can, because good typography
skills
will help you a lot when building any web
page.
After a quick assessment, we'll style our
portfolio.