[MUSIC]
We've learned about several different
types of values and
units in CSS but we haven't really
discussed color yet.
So far we've just used color keywords like
red or blue.
But I have a feeling you're more creative
than that.
And you wanna live in a world of digital
color.
[SOUND] There are a few different ways we
can define colors using CSS.
But we're going to learn about hexadecimal
colors in this project.
That looks and sounds complicated at
first.
So let's walk through it slowly.
Hexadecimal is a base 16 numbering system
rather than
the base ten number system that you are
used to.
After we count from zero to nine, we run
out
of our traditional numeric values and move
on to the letters.
A, B, C, D, E and F would represent the
numbers ten through 15
as a single digit or character.
So if we start counting as zero, that's 16
possibilities
for each place Now, in our normal base ten
numbering
system, we can combine two of the
numerals, zero through
nine, for a total of ten possible values
in each place.
If we multiply the number of possible
values in each place together,
we get a total of 100 possible numbers,
which represents zero through 99.
Now if we combine the two hexadecimal
values together in the same way we are
used to combining the numeral zero through
nine we can create
256 values instead of 100.
That's because each number is 16
digits and 16 multiplied by 16 is 256.
When we write hexadecimal colors there's a
place for red green and blue
which are the three colors we can combine
to make any color on a digital screen.
Each of these three colors consists of two
hexadecimal numbers.
For a total of six places.
The first two numbers are for red, the
second two
are for green, and the last two are for
blue.
The higher each of these values are,
the more of that color will be mixed in.
So for example, a hex value of all zeros
would be pure
black and a hex value of all F's would be
pure white.
A number in the middle, like all eight's,
would represent a middle gray.
These values start with a hash, or a
pound sign to denote that they're hex
decimal values.
We're going to create a green color using
the value 6ab47b.
If we break this down, the first pair of
values is a medium amount of red.
The second two values are a high amount of
green.
And the last two values are a medium
amount of blue.
So, with our knowledge of hexadecimal
colors, let's try one out.
I'm going to create some space to work,
here,
and just skip down our CSS file a little
bit.
And right here, I'm going to select an
anchor element.
Actually this is going to be all the
anchor elements on our page.
And I'm going to use the color property,
and I'm going to apply a hexadecimal value
of
6ab47b.
And if we hover over that hex decimal
value, you can see
that Work Spaces will automatically show
us what that color looks like.
Now, I want all of the links on my site to
be green.
But, throughout this project, you should
pick the colors that you like.
In fact, you'll see me type hexadecimal
colors like this pretty quickly.
It's not
because I'm magically able to type out
these colors from memory.
It's because I've already picked them out.
When picking colors, you'll need to take
some time experimenting, possibly in an
image editing tool like Photoshop.
I'm going to select our header and add two
new declarations.
Let's go ahead and select our header.
And we'll use the background property and
I'm going
to type in the same color that we used
here.
Actually I can just copy and paste it,
just like that.
And then I'm going to add a border-color
which is a property we haven't seen
before.
And I'm gonna add a new color here, which
is 599A68.
And that should do it.
Now I'm going to go ahead and save the
page and refresh over here.
And as you can see, Our header is now
green.
However it has the same color as our
links, so they're
disappearing, and we'll go ahead and fix
that in just a moment.
I'd also like you to notice that there
isn't a border really
appearing just yet, but we'll use that
border color later on.
Now, let's go ahead and fix the color of
those headlines.
To do that, I'm going to use a new
selector here, and I'll explain this in
just a minute.
So h1 followed by a coma, and h2, and
we're going to
set the color to white.
Now,
let's take a look at this syntax, because
I've done two new things here.
First, I've styled both our h1 and our h2
elements in the same style rule.
The
comma between two elements will break them
into two
separate selectors here.
So, this is actually separating
selectors and I could have say, a
descendant selector here.
So I can just select an anchor element if
it appeared inside the h1 just like that.
And it would separate it from my second
selector here.
So we're selecting h1 and separately we're
selecting the h2.
But we're applying the same set of style
rules to them.
Second, I've used some hexadecimal
shorthand here.
And I've only used three digits instead of
the normal six.
In this case, each digit will be used as
both digits for each color.
In other words, this is equivalent to
filling out all six
numbers with these values.
Of course these are the highest values
possible and have applied
it to all colors so that will give us a
white color.
Using shorthand for the hexadecimals and
the selectors here, is just a way
to save a little bit of time and increase
the clarity of your code.
Just to make sure you understand, the code
you see here would
be equivalent to the following.
If I were to type out an
h1.
And set it to the color
white, just like that, with our normal six
hexadecimal digits.
And then if I copied that and pasted it
and set that to an h2,
all of this code here is exactly
equivalent
to this code right here.
It's doing the exact same thing.
So this is much shorter than typing out
everything in longhand.
Now, let's go ahead and save this out,
switch over to the browser.
And refresh here and as you can see, we
now have our headlines visible.
However, our navigation is still here.
And it's not visible.
So if I highlight the page here, you can
just
barely make out this navigation links
which you can't see.
So, I want our navigation to have a
slightly darker green background
on mobile devices similar to the border
color that we'll use later on.
So let's go ahead and grab that border
color, just like that.
And then we
need to select our navigation, which we
haven't done yet.
So let's make a new selector.
And we'll say background and then paste in
that
color we just copied and end it with a
semicolon.
So let's go ahead and save that, switch
back to our preview and refresh.
And as you can see we have a slightly
darker
background applied but our navigation
links still aren't
very visible, there's not very much
contrast there.
So we want to change those to white as
well so that they're extra visible.
So in order to do that let's go ahead and
create another selector here.
That will select the anchor elements
inside of our nav.
And we're going to set the color again to
white, just like that.
So far so good.
However, we want these colors to stay
white no matter what.
Even if the site visitor has already
visited them.
To do that, we're going to create another
selector in this same rule using
a coma and we're going to select the
anchor elements again.
Now what we want to do here is add what's
called a
pseudo class to our second anchor element,
or our second selector here.
It's not a real class in our html but it's
basically a
state that the element can be put into
under the right conditions.
So let's go ahead and add a pseudo class.
I'm going to type a colon here, and then
I'm
going to type the word, visited.
So this is the visited pseudo class.
I'm going to save that out.
And if we go to our preview, and refresh
the page.
You can see that all of these links are
white.
And even if I click here and go back.
They still remain white, even if they've
been visited.