Now, there's a few more things we should
do for our nav links.
Specifically, we should make it obvious
which page the visitor
is currently on, by selecting and
highlighting the current nav link.
We'll do this by jumping back into our
mark up.
So we'll go into our html, here.
And we'll add an attribute called a class.
Now, I just mentioned a
class, but I didn't explain what it is.
So a class is similar to
an id, but the difference is that you can
have multiples of a same class
on a page.
All ids however, must be unique and
cannot be repeated on a single page.
So, let's go ahead and add that
class and I'm going to add it to
index.html or
the portfolio link here, because that's
the page that we're currently on.
And I'm going to say class and I'm going
to apply the class selected.
Now, just like ids, this can be anything
you want.
This isn't a predefined class.
This is just a class I made up.
So we'll need to apply some styling to
match it in our CSS.
We've could have used an id in
this particular instance, but adding a
class will
give us greater flexibility in case
there's a
strange navigational situation where we
want multiple selections.
In this case, we've applied the selected
class to our homepage link.
This will indicate to the site visitor
which page they're currently on.
So, let's save that and then jump into
our CSS, and utilize this class.
So,
I'm going to create a new rule here, and
say nav
a, and then apply the class.
And to do that we use dots.
I'll say .selected
and then we'll open up the rule here.
So, basically any
anchor element that's inside of our nav.
That
has the class selected applied to it.
We'll get
these style declarations.
So, we're just going
to apply a color here, and I'm going to
type out a new color.
And the value will be 32 for red, 67 for
the green and
3F for the blue.
So RGB.
Now, you've seen a few hexadecimal colors
so far, so without hovering over
this, I want you to try and guess what
this color might be.
Have you guessed it?
I'm going to hover over.
And guessed dark green, that's correct.
It's very similar to our other colors that
we've been applying previously.
So once again, just to review, if there's
an anchor element
with the class selected applied, it will
get this dark green color.
Want to also apply this dark green color
to
the hover state, which is another
pseudoclass similar to visited.
So, let's go ahead and break apart this
selector into two selectors.
And say nav anchor and then
apply the pseudoclass, hover.
So any time we hover
over this link with our cursor, it will
change to this particular color.
What does that mean?
Well, let's save this and go back to our
preview and refresh, and see what it looks
like.
As you can see the portfolio text is
a darker color now and that's because the
selected
class has been applied.
And, if I hover my cursor over the other
links here, you'll see that the hover
state activates and changes the color.
Pretty cool.
The last thing I want to style is the
background color and text color of our
body element.
Which basically encapsulates the entire
website.
We'll set the background to white and
the text color to grey.
That will make the text feel a
little less harsh because it will have
slightly lower contrast.
So, let's switch back to our CSS and I'll
scroll down here, I'm gonna type body and
then I'm gonna say, background color.
And I set
it to white, of course this is white by
default, but we want
to make sure that no other styling
overrides that for some strange reason.
We want to make absolutely sure that our
background
color is the color that we want it to be.
And then I'm gonna set the text color
using the color property And I'm going to
apply another shorthand hexidecimal value.
Now once again I want
you to try and guess what this color is
going to be.
And it's going to be this grey color.
So let's go ahead and save that, switch
over to our preview and refresh.
And if we scroll down the page here to
where we have some text, you can see that
it is now this light grey color.
Those are most of the colors that we'll
use on our website.
Later on, we'll add color in a few more
places.
Before we continue, let's review what
we've learned.