Inside of the selector, I'm going to add
some
new properties and values that we haven't
seen yet.
I'll type them out, and I want you to
follow along.
After we've typed them and seen the
result, I'll explain what they mean.
So I'm going to type max-width, and
give it a value of 940 pixels or px.
And then I'm going to type margin followed
by a zero
and then a space and then word auto.
Just like that.
Now, let's save and I'd like you to guess
as to
what this might do right before we refresh
the page here.
So, let's refresh.
And, as you can see, it looks like it's
centered
a lot of the stuff on our page here.
So everything that was inside of that div
is now centered.
But it has not affected things that were
outside of the div.
Now, let's investigate the code.
The first property, called max-width, is
closely related to the simpler and more
common property, width.
So we
could have just said width and then given
it a value, but
instead, we went with max-width.
We're basically saying
that we want the width to be no larger
than 940 pixels across.
However, the width could potentially be
smaller than that
if the browser were less than 400 pixels
wide.
This will come in handy when
we make more styling adjustments for
mobile and desktop devices.
The next declaration sets the margin for
the wrapper, or the spacing around the
element.
This is shorthand that will set the margin
on all four sides by using just two
values.
The first value sets the margin on the top
and the bottom of the element,
which in this case is just set to zero.
The unit doesn't matter in this case,
because if we were to set it to a pixel
value, like this, or
another unit such as a percentage value,
it would still mean the same thing.
So we can go ahead and just leave it at
zero without declaring a unit.
The second value, auto, will simply fill
in any space that's on the left or right
side of the margin.
In other words, if we were to take the
entire
width of the page and then subtract 940
pixels in
the middle, the rest of the space on the
left
and right is automatically filled in with
whatever's left over.
We don't need to worry about it.
I want you to be able to see what's
physically happening on the page,
so let's go ahead and color the
background.
Orange.
And I've used another shorthand property
here.
Instead of saying background color, I've
just said background.
There are more properties that we can add
to background, and we'll get into that
later, but for now, let's just save this
and see what this does to the page.
So if I refresh the page, you can see that
this div is now colored orange, and if we
scroll down,
you can see a little bit more of what this
looks like.
If I resize the browser, you'll see that
it adds a scroll
bar to the bottom of the page, but if I
move the scroll bar just
slightly, you'll see that it's only adding
that because the images are too large,
when in fact the div that we added, the
wrapper, fits perfectly inside of the
browser window here.
So, if the images were smaller, we
wouldn't get this scroll bar.
But what that means is that this element,
this wrapper, is flexing with the browser
window.
It has a maximum width of 940 pixels, but
it can get infinitely
smaller than that.
One problem here is that our text runs
right up against the edge of the
element, and therefore will be right
against the
edge of the browser window at smaller
sizes.
We need to add some spacing around the
inside
of the element called padding in order to
fix this.
So, lets go ahead and add some padding
right after our margin here.
So I'll say padding
zero and then the second value will be 5%.
Similar to margin we've used two values
here.
The first value represents the top and
bottom,
so there's zero padding on the top and
bottom.
The second value represents the left and
right.
In our case, we're applying 5% padding to
both sides of the element.
This will be 5% of the total width of the
wrapper element itself.
Let's go ahead and save this and then
refresh
the preview to see what this did for us.
As you can see, we now have some spacing
on the inside of
our element, as well as some spacing on
the outside of our element.
If
I go ahead and resize the browser, you'll
notice that the
padding is changing ever so slightly,
because it's only 5%,
but it's still definitely changing and
adjusting to the width of the browser.
This will be important later on, because
not all browser windows are the same size.
For example,
the browser window will be much smaller
than
what it looks like on our desktop device
here.