From this point forward, we're actually
going to
be building the mobile version of our site
first.
This might seem a little bit
counter-intuitive, but modern websites
are built with mobile devices in mind from
the start.
There's two factors feeding into this.
[SOUND].
First, it's much easier to build a mobile
website
when you're fist starting out because,
it's much simpler.
You don't have to worry about tons of
complex features,
advertisements, complex layouts, and so
on.
Instead, you have to reduce a website to
its pure essence.
Then, when you move your design up to more
robust
platforms like tablets and desktops, you
can progressively enhance your website.
This is easier than creating a really
complex website on the desktop, and
then trying to figure out how jam that
experience onto a tiny screen.
Second, it's very important to pay
attention to the
mobile experience, the mobile web is not a
small platform.
In fact, mobile browsing is on track to
eclipse desktop browsing,
if it hasn't already done so, by the time
you watch this.
It really is moving fast.
So, it's imperative that we design a great
experience on mobile
from the start, and work our way up to the
desktop.
For your own reference, here's what my
finished mobile website is going to look
like.
Now, let's jump back into the code and
remove
that ugly orange background we were using
for testing purposes.
Now, let's remove the orange background on
our wrapper,
because we don't actually need that in our
project.
That was just for the purposes of an
example.
And, let's close
out this portion of the lesson by styling
our headline elements.
To do that, we'll first need to select
them.
I'm going to apply an ID called Logo to
the anchor
element, that wraps them.
So, to do that we need to switch over to
our HTML, and inside of this anchor
element, that wraps our headlines,
we need to type ID, and we're going to
call it Logo.
And we'll save that, and then back in our
CSS
here, I created a little bit of space
after our wrapper.
And I'm going to, again, using ID
selector, using the HASH or pound sign,
and select the Logo, and then, inside of
the selector, I'm going
to make a few declarations.
And first I'm using the property,
text-align with the value center.
We'll go over that in just a moment.
And then I'm setting the margin to 0.
Now lets explain what we just did here.
I've used the text-align property to align
the text, so just like
in a word processing program we can align
our text to the left,
right, or center.
I want my text to be centered, so I've
typed out the value center.
You've probably noticed by now that some
properties take values that are
numeric and some take words, which are
commonly called keywords.
So for example, center, or none, are known
as keywords.
Some properties like margin can even take
both
key words and numeric values, as you see
here.
When you're first starting to learn CSS,
this can
be a little bit tricky, but if there are
keywords that you can use to fill a value,
WorkSpaces can help you with its code
completion features.
You'll notice that when I finished typing
text-align, and I'll do that
again just so you can see it here.
It will suggest some of those keywords to
complete it.
If I just use the arrow keys, I can move
up and down the selection here, and I can
select Center and hit Enter to actually
type that out for me automatically.
I don't need to do that manually, if I
don't want to.
With practice and a few websites, you'll
start to memorize these.
But, don't feel bad if you need to refer
back to
these videos or use a search engine to
look them up.
Next, I've applied a value of 0 to our
margin here.
I don't want this element to have any
spacing around the edges, so if I just
apply a 0, it will apply it to all four
sides of our element.
Now, if we go ahead and save this file
here, switch over to our preview, and
refresh, you'll see that first, the orange
background has been removed,
but secondly, our headline elements have
been centered on the page.
We've covered a lot of new CSS properties
and values.
So, let's pause for a code challenge, to
make sure that we didn't miss anything.