We're ready to upload our website to our
server.
In order to do that, we'll need some
special
software that can use what's called the
SFTP protocol.
SFTP can mean a few things.
But often, it stands for secure file
transfer protocol.
In other words, we're going to be
transferring our files using a secure
connection.
After we pointed our domain to our server
we should be able to navigate to our
domain in
a web browser and it should look something
like this.
So if I type in treehousewebsite.com,
which is the domain I purchased.
We can see this Index of text, a
CGI bin folder and some information about
the server.
We want to replace this with our website
that we spent so long creating.
So, let's get started.
In order to do that,
we need to first download some FTP
software to transfer our files to the
server.
I'm going to use FTP software called
Cyberduck, available at Cyberduck.io.
You can also download it from the Mac App
Store,
but there are download links here for
Windows and for Mac.
So be sure to choose the download link
appropriate for your operating system.
I'm going
to choose the Mac download, and this might
be a good time
to pause the video while you wait for the
download to finish.
And after it's done, I can choose Show in
Finder.
Which should be Windows Explorer, if
you're on Windows.
I can then double-click the zip file and
it will unzip CyberDuck.
And now, I can drag it to my Applications
folder.
Again, this installation process will be
slightly different
on Windows, but it should be the same
principle.
Once you've installed CyberDuck, you can
open it up.
And if you're on a Mac like me, you might
see a
window that looks like this, asking if you
really wanna open it.
Just go ahead and click Open.
And the first time you open Cyberduck it
should look something like this.
Your bookmarks
might be slightly different than mine but
that's okay.
Just click Open Connection and then we
need to put in our SFTP credentials.
So instead of file transfer protocol,
choose SFTP from the drop down.
Which means SSH file transfer protocol,
which is sometimes also called
secure file transfer protocol because
indeed it is more secure than FTP.
So choose SFTP and then it will ask us to
put in a server.
If you recall, we received an email
earlier from student hosting with the
FTP address, as well as our username, and
just below this is my password.
But I don't want to reveal my password,
for obvious reasons, you
should use your own username and password
as well as your own domain.
So
I'm going to put in my FTP address, which
in this case
happens to be my domain.
Then I need to fill in the port number.
In this case, the port number is 18765.
Again, that's 18765.
Then type in your username.
My username is treehous without the e,
because the server abbreviates it to eight
characters in this particular case.
And then I'm going to put in my password,
and then I'll click Connect.
You might see a dialogue box that looks
like this.
It says, unknown host key for your domain.
That's perfectly fine, we want to allow
this,
and you might want to check always allow
this.
And when you first log into your server it
should
look something like this.
We want to navigate to the www folder
because that's
where our website will live on the World
Wide Web.
Let's double click that folder, and here's
that CGI bin folder that we saw
previously.
We don't need this folder for our project,
so right click on it and choose delete.
And then click delete to confirm.
And now, we need to upload our files to
this window here.
How do we do that?
Well let's go back to our work space and
from here we can
choose File > Download Workspace.
And it
will download it to a zip file I can show
this in the Finder.
Double click it to unzip it and when you
unzip
the file, it should give you a folder
called download.
We don't want to just copy this download
folder directly to CyberDuck.
Rather we want to open it up and only copy
its contents.
So don't just drag this over to CyberDuck.
Make sure you grab the contents of the
download folder.
And then you can drag and drop it over to
CyberDuck.
So I'll drag the contents of the Download
folder over to my WWW folder in CyberDuck.
Again I need to click Allow for the host
key fingerprint, and then it
will log in and start uploading my files.
Once the upload has completed,
I can click on my website, refresh the
page, and as
you can see our site is now live on the
web.
I can click on these images and they'll
enlarge just like you'd expect.
And I can also click around to the
different
pages and they're also there just as you'd
expect.
So now anyone in the world can type in
your custom domain and see your website.
Our website is now live on the web and
anyone with an
internet connection can type the address
into a browser and access it.
There's still a few more things you should
know about making basic
website before we move on to a more
advanced material.
But we'll cover that next.