Classes and IDs allow us to specifically target elements
based on their class or ID attributes.
The main difference between a class and ID is that IDs are unique
and they're used to identify one element on a page.
Whereas a class can be used to classify and target more than one element.
So first up let's talk about selecting elements with CSS class selectors.
A class selector targets an element based on its class attribute.
So in our HTML file, let's go ahead and add
class attributes and values to some of our elements.
We'll then create a few styles for them in our style sheet
because currently our page has no author styles applied.
So in our HTML file, we'll start with the first DIV in the document.
So we'll go ahead and give it a class attribute
followed by an = sign and a set of quotation marks.
Now naming the class is up to us and it's usually good practice to give classes
meaningful names that explain what they do and what their purpose is.
Because this DIV contains or wraps the other elements in the document,
we'll go ahead and give it a class name container.
So we'll save our HTML file and we'll go into our style.css file
where we'll need to create the class selector or container.
Classes are defined by using the dot character followed by the class name.
So we'll first type a dot followed by container and a set of curly braces.
We'll then create a few styles for our new container class.
So I'll give it a width property with the value 740 pixels
followed by a margin property and the value auto
which will center our DIV element on the page.
So when we save our CSS file and refresh the browser,
we see the width of the container element reduced to 740 pixels
and it's now centered in the browser.
So next, let's add a class to our header elements.
Now we could may be just use this header element type selector to select it
but let's instead give it the class name name header
because again, we'll want to give it a meaningful class name
and since we know this will always be the main header in our page
or website, the main header class name communicates that very clearly.
So we'll go ahead and type name-header
So we'll save the HTML file and go back into the style sheet
where we'll need to create the class selector for main-header.
So again, I'll type a dot followed by main-header and a set of curly braces
then I will give it a height property with a value of 110 pixels
followed by color white and finally--
a background property with the value royal blue.
So when we save the style sheet and refresh our browser,
we can see that our header is now 110 pixels tall,
the text color is white, and the background is royal blue.
Back in our HTML file, let's add a class attribute
to the next DIV element in the document
and we'll go ahead and give it the value main-content.
I'm giving it the class name main-content because the DIV contains
the main content on the page like headings and paragraphs.
So in our style.css file, I'll create the selector for main-content
and I will give it a padding property with the value of 20 pixels
and a background value of light gray.
So I'll save the style sheet and when we refresh the browser,
we see that light gray background and the 20 pixels of padding
separating the content from the edges of the DIV.
Finally, let's add a class to our footer element.
We'll give it the class name name footer because again
like main header, it's a meaningful class name
since this will always be the main footer in our page.
So we'll save our HTML file and in our style sheet,
we'll create our class selector for main-footer.
I will give it a height of 100 pixels, a text color of white,
and I will give it a background value with the shade of black.
So when we save our style sheet and refresh the browser,
there we see our new footer styles.
CSS class selectors are very useful
because they can be reused throughout a page.
So multiple elements can share the same class
and an element can also have multiple classes applied to it.
So for example, let's create a new class selector named base
where I will give it some top padding.
I'll also make the text color white.
I'll align the text center and give it a font size of 24 pixels.
So I'll save this style sheet and go into our HTML file
where we then add the new base class value to any of these classes.
We'll just need to separate them with a space.
So we'll go ahead and add it to the main_header and main-footer values.
So again, I will just add a space followed by base
and in our footer, I will add a space followed by base.
When we save our HTML file and refresh the browser,
there we see those new base styles applied to the header and the footer.
So it applies those new styles on top of the ones they already have.
Like with type selectors, we can also create descended selectors with classes.
So for example in our CSS file, I will select main-content.
I will follow it with a space then select every paragraph inside main_content
where I will give them a font size of 21 pixels and a line height of 1.5
and a margin top value of 32 pixels.
When we save the style sheets and review it in the browser,
I'll click refresh, we can see how the paragraph text is much larger
and the line of texts are spaced out with the line height and margins.
So next, let's talk about ID selectors.
An ID selector targets an element based on its ID attribute.
What makes IDs different from classes is that IDs are unique to the page.
So an element can only have one ID
and a page can only have one element with the same ID name.
So in our HTML file, let's go ahead and change this name
content + attribute in our mark up here to an ID attribute.
So now, because our DIV already had an ID applied,
we can no longer add IDs to it and we cannot use this main-content ID
anywhere else in this HTML file like we could with classes.
So I'll save our HTML file and next, we'll need to change our CSS selector.
ID selectors are created by using the # symbol.
So in our style sheet, we'll just need to switch
the period in our selector here with the # symbol.
So when we save this and refresh the browser, notice how the
main_content DIV element still has its padding and background styles applied.
The paragraphs, however, have lost their font size, line height, and margins
because we've changed their parent element to an ID.
So in our style sheet, we'll simply need to adjust this descended selector
by changing the main-content class selector to an ID.
So now when we refresh, our paragraphs are once again
styled with the larger font size, line height, and top margins.
We can apply both a class and an ID to an element
but keep in mind that IDs carry more specificity than classes do.
So if an element has an ID and a class applied,
the styles defined in the ID selector will always carry more weight
than the styles defined in the class selector.
So we'll need to make sure we don't share properties between classes and IDs.
IDs also have browser functionality .
They can be used as what are called fragment identifiers
for creating landmarks or anchors in pages.
I'll show you what I mean.
So if we give the header at the top of our page here an ID attribute
and the value top, then at the very bottom of the page,
we'll go ahead and add a link and we will give it an HREF value of #top.
Whenever we click on a link with an HREF value of #top,
the browser will locate the element with the ID of top
and it will jump right to that section of the page.
So for the sake of this example, I'll go ahead and increase
the height of our main-content DIV to about 800 pixels.
So we can really see how this works.
So when I save both files and refresh the browser,
notice how our height has been extended
and when we scroll down and click our back to top link here,
the browser takes us right back up to the top of the page
because we've instructed it to find the element with the ID of top
which in our case is the header.