[Deep Dive]
[Web Typography: Responsive Text and Vertical Rhythm Part 1 with Guil Hernandez]
[Guil Hernandez]: As we've just learned,
the web has caught up with typography in a remarkable way,
and it has become a rapidly evolving area of CSS.
But good web typography
is also knowing when to be flexible.
By default, text is fluid.
So, depending on our approach,
responsive typography can be easily achieved,
and there are many CSS features and tools
that can help us maintain a consistent baseline,
make a font size flexible,
or respond to different viewport sizes.
So let's get started and learn how
we can make our text look great in any context.
These days, there seems to be countless combinations
of devices, operating systems,
and screen sizes and resolutions
that can render text differently.
Some differences are more subtle than others.
Although text is naturally fluid,
it's not exactly a one-size-fits-all solution.
For example, a heading may look great
and proportionately sized
on a desktop browser,
but look entirely different on a tablet
or mobile device.
The same can happen with body text,
as font sizes, line length, and line height
may start losing their rhythm
and balance proportions
which can ultimately lead
to illegible and unreadable text.
We need to consider how our text will look
in most contexts.
Are the word shapes still enticing to the reader?
Is the typographic color still present?
Well the good news is
that responsive or adaptive typography
isn't all that difficult to achieve.
We just need to take some time
to think through how our text should respond
to changes in screen size
and then implement those changes.
So let's go over a simple example
we can apply to just about any project.
Here we have a simple, one-column
text layout
with a Main Title heading
and a few subheadings.
So far, the layout looks pretty good,
but there is much more we can do
to enhance the text
by improving readability
and the vertical spacing.
Currently, our line lengths
are fixed, and the font sizes are set
in pixels.
So first, let's set our font sizes
to relative em units so that they scale relative
to the base font size.
I want to change the body text
to a bigger font size,
because the current font size of 16 pixels
seems a little small.
So let's go ahead and make it 18 pixels.
We'll use the target divided by context
equals result formula
to convert our body font size
to ems.
[typing]
So 18 divided by 16
gives us a body font size
of 1.125em.
[typing]
This establishes a new context
for our font sizes and line height.
What we did was make the new font size
1.125 times larger
than the browser's default size
of 16 pixels.
Sizing body text shouldn't be entirely based
on personal preference.
We need to consider things like reading distances
and the screens or devices it may be viewed in.
Desktop screens are generally further away
than tablets or most mobile devices,
and it's a larger screen,
so the font size should be slightly bigger.
Eighteen pixels seems to be a good size
for this typeface we chose--
PT Serif--
so we'll keep that size for our main body text.
But we can also make our headings
a little larger, too.
When sizing type,
it's not good practice to
just select a random font size
that we think would look good.
We probably could get away with it here,
since it's a simple page with 3 heading sizes
and body text,
but it's good to use a typographic scale,
because it helps us achieve
a consistent hierarchy,
and it ensures that our design
stays harmonious in every way.
Here is an example of the traditional
typographic scale,
which increases gradually in increments
of 1, 2, 3,
and, finally, 12,
to ensure consistency in the proportions.
We'll go ahead and base our font sizes
on this scale, which they already are,
we just need to convert our headings
from pixels to em units.
Using our new font-size context
of 18px,
we'll change our heading size here
from 72px
to 4em.
For our Heading 2, we can change that
to 2em,
which is twice the 18-pixel font size.
And just below in our Heading 3,
we'll change it from 24px
to 1.333.
And finally, for our Code Example text,
we can set a font size,
but this time we want to set it
back to 16 pixels.
So instead of just typing "16 pixels,"
we can use the "rem" unit,
which stands for "root em"
which just resizes it back
to the base root unit
of 16px.
When we refresh the page,
there we see our new font sizes
set in ems.
Optimal readability requires a certain amount of control
over the line length.
So next, we'll need to create a fluid line length
that resizes whenever the browser width
is reduced
or when the page is viewed on smaller screen sizes,
like on mobile devices.
Because, as we can see here,
the width of our lines
are fixed, because currently
our containing element
or "wrap div"
is set to a fixed width
of 600px.
In order to make it fluid,
we'll need to define the width in percentages.
Fiddling around with percentage numbers,
I came up with a width
of 58,
which closely matches the 600-pixel width.
We'll give it a max width of 58%.
That way it cannot grow any more than that.
So now when we refresh this,
the lines of text are fluid
and resize to 58%
of the viewport width.
But notice when we are at a smaller width,
the lines of text are now
too short.
So we once again need to adjust a few things here.
At the bottom of our style sheet,
we have 2 media queries
and that's all we'll need for this particular example.
If you want to learn more about media queries,
take a look at the Deep Dive on media queries
or check out Allison Grayce's series
on responsive web design.
But, here, we'll need to make things adaptive
with as few breakpoints as possible.
In fact, we'll only adjust it
at 1 breakpoint.
So whenever the browser is reduced
below 600px,
the max width of our wrap
will increase to 85%.
We'll refresh that.
Now you can see how
it adjusts right here.
So the line of text is no longer too short.
It's actually quite readable.
Next let's adjust the font size of the body text
so that it's not too big
if the screen is narrower
than 600px.
We'll just need to reset
the body font size to 1em.
One em is equivalent to 16px,
so this becomes our new context
for font sizes when the viewport is less
than 600-pixels wide.
Back in our browser, we can see that
when the page
is reduced below 600px,
the paragraph text and headings
scale down accordingly and still maintain
their proportions.
But notice the line lengths are now too long,
and they keep increasing in length
the wider the browser gets.
So we'll need one more media query
to adjust this and make sure the text
doesn't get any wider
once the viewport is wider than
980px,
because that will still preserve our readable line length.
So in our media query here,
we'll once again select our wrap div,
and we will give it a max width
of 600px.
This will give us that optimal reading length
of about 60 characters.
[typing]
Now if our browser exceeds
a width of 980px,
the text will stay fixed
at 600px,
and the line lengths won't increase.