[CSS Foundations with Guil Hernandez: Selectors: Deep Dive]
Selectors are one of the most important and powerful parts of CSS.
They are essentially patterns that allow us
to target HTML elements and apply styles to them.
When we define a selector in our style sheet,
we're instructing the browser to match
every instance of that selector in the HTML
Now, we already saw selectors that work in the previous stage
when we created simple selectors to change
the colors of headings, paragraphs, and backgrounds.
In this Deep Dive, we'll learn the different ways we can define a selector
as selectors can be defined based on an element's type, its class, or ID name,
or even its position in the document.
So first, let's get stated with basic type selectors
then we'll get more specific as we go.
So here we have a simple HTML document containing
an h1, h2, and a few paragraph elements
and we can see what it's looking like in the browser so far.
Besides the default browser styles, no author styles have been applied just yet.
So let's add a few styles of our own by first creating a new CSS file.
So in our text editor, I'll go ahead and open a new file
and I will save it style.css and save it in the CSS folder.
Next, we'll need to link our new CSS file to our HTML document.
So over in our index.html file under the title tag,
I will add link rel=stylesheet followed by HREF
and inside, I will add the path to the new style sheets.
So we know it's in the CSS directory
and the file name is style.css
So, I'll go ahead and save our HTML file and go back into style.css
where we'll be creating a few simple styles using CSS properties
and values that you might not be familiar with just yet
but don't worry because we'll be covering those properties
and values in greater detail in the values and unit stage.
For now, we'll only need to understand how CSS selectors work.
So the very first selector we'll cover is called the universal selector.
It's called a universal selector because it selects every element on the page at once
and applies the styles we set.
The universal selector is a very powerful selector
because it takes precedence overall other selectors as we'll soon find out.
So to create a universal selector, we simply use an * as our selector
followed by a set of curly braces.
Inside this curly braces is where we write the properties
and values we'd like to apply universally to our page.
So for example, I will start with a margin property and a value of 0
and I will follow that with a padding property where I also give it value 0
and a color property with the value red.
Now in the previous stage, we learned that browsers have
a built in style sheet called the user agent style sheet
that by default, applies padding and margins to the body, headings,
list, paragraphs, and other elements on the page.
By setting the margin and padding to 0,
we're telling the browser to remove all margins
and padding from every element on the page
then change their font color from the default black to red.
So let's go ahead and save this file and take a look at it in the browser.
When I refresh the browser, we can see how all the padding and margins
have been removed from all heading and paragraph elements on the page
and the font color is now red.
Now, because this is a very powerful selector,
we'll need to be careful how we use it.
For example, inheritance in CSS values
will not work when we use the universal selector.
So we loose that inheritance from parent elements
we discussed in the previous stage
because the universal selector trumps any form of inherited styles.
Now because of that, we'll need to write a lot of extra CSS for child elements.
So for now, we'll go ahead and remove this
universal selector rule from our style sheet.
But in a later video, we'll go over the ways the selector can be useful.
So next up, we'll talk about type selectors.
A type selector is what we use to select an element type on the page.
They're also called element selectors
because we only use the elements HMTL tags as the selector.
So we can use any of the HTML or HTML5 tags as selectors in our CSS.
So for example, if we want to add a background color and padding to our page
in our CSS file, we can simply select the body element by typing body
followed by a set of curly braces.
Again, inside the curly braces, we can then declare the
background color property and we'll go ahead and give it a color value of light blue.
Below that, I will add a padding property with the value of 40 pixels.
So when I save this and refresh it in the browser,
notice how the background color of our page has changed to light blue
and there is this padding separating the content from the edges of the page.
Because the body selector we just wrote instructed the browser to change
the background color from white to light blue and add 40 pixels padding.
So again, if we needed to select an add styles to the heading 1 on the page
in our style sheet, we'll simply type H1 to select the heading 1 element
and inside the curly braces, we can add the properties and values we want to declare.
So this time, I will give it a color property
and the color value will be a darker shade of blue.
I will also change the font size to 40 pixels.
So when I save this and refresh the browser,
we can see how our heading 1 has turned to blue
and the font size has increased to 40 pixels.
Next, we'll use another type selector to target the h2 in our page.
So back in our style.css file, we'll type h2 to select the h2 element
and inside the curly braces, we will add a color property
and at this time, we'll make the color value a light shade of red.
So when we save this and review it in the browser,
there we see our heading 2 turned red.
Now, let's say we want to select and style every paragraph on the page.
Well, we can easily accomplish that with the type selector.
So in our style.css file, we'll simply type p to select every paragraph
and we will give it a color property with the value white
followed by 10 pixels of padding,
and we will add a background color and the value will be blue.
Again, don't worry if you don't understand some of these properties just yet
because we'll covering them in the next few stages.
So when we save our CSS and refresh the browser,
we can see how the paragraph type selector
we just created matches every paragraph on the page
and they're now styled with the color, padding,
and background properties we defined.
We can also combine type selectors
to create what are called descendant selectors.
A descendant selector selects an element that is a descendant of another element.
So for example, in our HTML file, we can see the span element nested inside the h1.
So we can say that the span element is a descendant of the h1.
Now, because of this, we create a descendant selector
that only targets the span element inside the h1.
To create a descendant selector, we'll need to use
two or more selectors separated by wide space.
So in our CSS file, we'll first type h1 to select the heading 1
followed by a space then the span type selector.
Inside the curly braces, I'll add a color property
and I'll give it a dark blue color value.
So when we save the CSS file and refresh the browser,
we can see that it only affected that span element inside the heading 1
In our HTML file, notice that there are other span elements nested inside
the paragraphs and in the heading 2 element that were not selected.
Now, if we want to style the span element inside of our paragraphs,
all we need to do is create a new descendant selector for that.
So in our CSS, we will type p to select all paragraphs
followed by a space then span.
Next, I will add a color property with the color black
and I will give it font-weight of bold.
So I'll save this CSS file and when we refresh the browser,
we can see that the only span element that turned black and bold
are the ones nested inside our paragraphs.
Now, if we only want to style the span element inside
our h2 instead of the one up here in the h1,
we simply change our selector.
So in our CSS, I will simply change h1 to h2
and when we save it and refresh the browser, there we go.
Now the span in the h2 is the one that turns navy blue.