Combinators explain the relationship between 2 or more selectors.
We've actually used combinators in previous lessons
when we created descendant selectors
because the space between the 2 selectors is considered a combinator.
Other combinators we can use are the greater-than sign,
a plus sign, or a tilde symbol--let's learn how.
In a CSS selector, the greater than sign is referred to as a "Child Combinator".
and selectors that use child combinators are called "Child Selectors"
because they target elements that are direct children of other elements.
So let's create our first child selector that will only target
the links that are direct children of our "div" with the class "main"
which, as you can see here in the browser, is outlined by the solid 1 pixel border.
So remember, direct children are only those elements
that are directly nested inside the parent.
So, in our style.css file, we'll first rate the main CSS class selector
then use the greater than sign as our combinator
followed by the "a" element selector.
We'll then give it a color property and the value red.
So, when we saved our style sheet and refresh the browser,
We see the the 2 direct child links styled with the red color,
while the links nested inside the paragraphs remained unchanged
because those links are direct children of the paragraph elements not the main "div."
It's also important that we do not confused child selectors
with the descendant selector we covered in an earlier lesson.
I'll show you what happens if we remove the child combinator in our selector.
So, by removing it, it's now a descendant selector
because we're using a space between the 2 selectors.
So, when we save this and refresh the browser,
we can see how all the link in the page have turned red
because we've change our selector to target every "a" element descendant
of our main "div" instead of the ones that are direct children.
So let's go ahead and add it back in to keep this a child selector.
Up next, the plus sign combinator is called an "Adjacent Sibling Combinator"
and selectors that use them are called "Adjacent Sibling Selectors"
because they target an element "next sibling" on the page.
so, the one that immediately follows the element.
So for example in our HTML file,
the "h2" adjacent sibling is this paragraph element right below
because it immediately follows it in the document.
So we can specifically target this paragraph element
with an adjacent sibling selector.
So in our style sheet, let's create an adjacent sibling selector
by first selecting the "h2" element.
Then, use the plus sign as our combinator followed by the "P" element selector.
I'll then give it color property for the value white
I'll add a little bit of padding,
and, finally, I will give it a background color of royal blue.
So, when we save our style sheet, when we refresh the browser,
notice how only those paragraphs immediately following an "h2"
have the new color and padding styles applied.
Now, if we reverse the selector by placing the paragraph selector before the "h2",
We'll save it, and when we bring it up in the browser,
we can see that, now, it's only targeting the heading 2
that immediately follows a paragraph.
The second heading 2 is an immediate sibling of this link, so it remains unchanged.
Finally, if we replace this adjacent sibling combinator with the tilde symbol,
This selector now becomes a "General Sibling Selector"
The tilde symbol is called a "General Sibling Combinator"
because it's use to target other sibling.
But this time, it not only targets an immediate sibling.
It actually targets every specified sibling that follows an element.
So, with this selector, we're telling the browser
to target every sibling paragraph that follows a heading 2.
So, when we save this and bring it up in the browser,
we see the styles applied to every paragraph
that comes after the "h2" elements.
Now, even if we remove the second heading 2 in our HTML file,
in the browser, we can see how the general sibling selector
will still target these last 2 paragraphs
because they're still siblings of the heading 2 above.