We're almost done with the basics.
Before we move onto styling other pages
and screen sizes, we need to
build out a navigation and finish up a few
other things on the page.
First, let's fix up our header.
Right now, there is some odd space up at
the top.
That's happening because the first level
headline is pushing it out
of the way with it's margin, and there's
just not enough space.
So let's go ahead and find our heading
here, and then over the top,
we'll select our header.
And I'm going to do a few things.
First, I'm going to float it to the left.
I'm going to set the margins so that zero
on the top, zero on
the right, 30 pixels on the bottom, and
zero on the left.
So there's four values there, for top,
right, bottom, left.
Then we'll set the padding, similarly
we'll use four values; so five pixels and
then zero, zero, zero making sure to put
spaces in between to separate the values.
And again that's five pixels on the top,
and then zero on the right bottom
and left and if you're having trouble
remembering the syntax when you use four
values like this.
Just remember that you start at the top
and then you go clockwise.
So you go from top, right, bottom, left.
So let me explain this code in a little
bit more detail.
Floating it to the left doesn't have any
practical use right
now but it will later on when we style our
desktop layout.
So stay tuned for that.
Setting our margins keeps the header
separated
from other content at least on the bottom.
But removes the problematic margins that
we had on the top, previously.
Then, we add some padding on the top to
separate the
text without actually removing the margin
from the top of the page.
Now, there's one
more thing we need to do to make this
work.
We need to set a width of 100%.
It's now a floated element which means it
doesn't have an explicit width anymore.
We want to specifically say that this
element should stretch across the entire
page so we've set a width of 100%.
Now, let refresh the page, and
see our work.
It looks good.
Now lets dig into this navigation.
Right now our navigation is an unordered
list.
So we're actually going to use a similar
technique that
we used on our gallery, which is also an
unordered list.
First, I'm going to select the unordered
list element and
set some margins on the left and right,
remove any padding,
and then remove any bullet points.
So let's scroll down, to our navigation
here,
and inside of our navigation element we
have our
un-ordered list and that's what we'll want
to style.
We'll want set list style to none even
though
there were no bullet points that we could
see.
We still wanna make sure that we are
removing those anyway.
Just in case.
Then we are going to set the margin to
zero and ten pixels,
so that zero on the top and bottom and ten
pixels on
the left and right, and then we'll set the
padding to zero.
Now, I'm going to use a new property
I haven't shown you before, and it's
called display.
Every element has a display property by
default,
and it's set to either block or inline.
Block level element will take up space in
the page,
and appear to push other things out of the
way.
These are things like sections, divs, and
many other elements.
Inline elements are mostly just text.
For example, when we add an anchor element
inside of a paragraph, it
doesn't push all of the words out of the
way or push anything to the next line,
it just appears in the same line, or
inline,
As the rest of the text, hence the term
inline.
We're actually going to use another
property, though, called inline block.
This will allow us to have these items
side by side, just like inline
elements, but they'll retain other block
level features, such as having
a width and height.
So, lets say nav, list items,
display in line, block.
Now lets save and refresh the page to see
how that looks.
Awesome, now all of our links Are in a
nice, neat row, just like that.
So in other words, they're in line with
one another but they
still have some block level properties not
just having a width and height.