Now, let's style our anchor elements.
We don't have to be overly specific with
this selector, because there
are only one set of anchor elements inside
of our nav element.
So, we'll scroll down here, and we'll say
nav a.
And we'll set the font weight to 800.
[SOUND] And we'll
set the padding to 15 pixels and 10
pixels.
Remember the font weight property can be
set to either normal or bold.
But it can also be set to a specific
number.
When we included our fonts from Google
previously, this was one of the font
weights that we picked out and I think
this is an appropriate place to
use it.
Next, we've added some padding on all
sides of our links.
This will make the click targets
on them easier to hit with a mouse of a
touch screen device.
So, if we switch back, and refresh, you
can see that our links are now much
bolder and they have more space around
them.
And, when I hover over, you can see that a
lot of the space around the text is now
also clickable.
Which makes it just, a little bit easier,
to hit these tap targets, when you're
on a mobile device, or click on them, if
you're on a desktop like I am.
Before we wrap this section up,
there's one more loose end that we should
tie up.
Down in our footer, you'll notice that our
social media icons are pretty large.
We want them to be smaller and less
prominent.
These icons are about twice the size that
they need to be.
That's because we want these images to
look sharp
on high resolution displays that have
double pixel density.
By creating the images at twice the size
and then resizing them downward
using CSS, the pixels will still be there
for high res displays.
These types of high res displays aren't
everywhere yet, but they're starting
to become more common in mobile devices,
as well as desktop devices.
In order to do this, we actually need to
switch back to our HTML,
so that we can properly select, each one
of these.
On our first link, just after the alt
attribute, I'm going to add a class
attribute, called social-icon.
Then I'm going to copy that class
attribute and paste
it on our second link as well.
Now we could have selected these in a
slightly
different way, for example we could say
footer And
then, anchor, but I wanted to show you how
classes can be used multiple times on a
page.
So in this case, we're going to create a
CSS class, and it will be applied, to both
items.
So let's save our HTML, and go back to our
CSS.
And in our footer here, let's skip down
and make
some room to work.
And I'm going to select our social icons.
And I'm going to give them explicit width
of 20 pixels, an explicit height
of 20 pixels, and a margin of zero and
five pixels.
So, that's zero on top and bottom, and
five on the
left and right, which will give some
separation between the two icons.
The width and height is half the size of
the icons.
They're about 40 pixels each.
So, resizing them downward will add more
detail into a denser area.
Let's go back, refresh the page.
And as you can see, our icons are now much
smaller and at a more reasonable size.
Great work.
We've made a lot of progress on our site.
At this point, you've learned most of the
skills you
need to build almost any type of simple
web page.
Learning HTML and CSS can be very
challenging at first, but, with continued
practice you'll find that the elements and
properties become second nature to you.
We still need to create the other pages,
but that will be
much easier now that we have most of the
styling done for
common elements, like the header and
footer.
Before we continue, let's review what
we've learned.