Now, let's move on.
The last thing we need to style are the
paragraphs inside of our list.
We've already done a little bit here, but
there's still more that we can do.
So, I'm going to select our gallery.
Select the list items.
Select the anchor elements inside of those
list items.
And select the paragraphs inside of the
anchor elements.
So, just to review our HTML.
We're going from our gallery into the list
items, into the anchor elements.
And then selecting these paragraphs right
here.
So that's where the styling will be
applied.
Let's give them a margin of zero, because
paragraphs do have
some margin by default, so we want to zero
that out.
We'll set the padding to 5%, just to space
them out a little bit.
We want to decrease the font size because
they're a little bit large.
So we'll set it to 0.75 ems.
And then, finally, we're going to adjust
the color.
And we'll set it to bdc3c7.
So, if we save that out, switch back to
browser.
And refresh.
You can see that now we have this lighter
gray color here applied to our links as
well.
So, whether the text is linked or unlinked
this is the color that will be displayed.
We've set the margin to zero in favor
of adding padding around the image.
This is better because margin has a
tendency to
push elements even if they're side of the
parent container.
In other words, they push elements where
they shouldn't.
And finally, you can see the effect that
the font size declaration had.
It decreased the size of the fonts here,
so they're a little bit more readable.
Go ahead and resize, and see what that
looks like.
Once again there's still more work to do
on
the desktop layout, but we will get to
that later.
For now we're just concerned with kind of
the mobile view here.
So far so good.
There's one last thing we need to fix
before we move our attention on to other
things.
If you look at the footer you'll notice
that it's somehow up
inside of the gallery here.
That's because it's behaving exactly as
it's been told.
It's simply flowing around these other
floated elements.
We need this footer to be cleared of any
influence from
the other floats on both the left and the
right sides.
So, let's find our footer and add a
property called clear.
We'll set the value of clear to both
because
we want it to be cleared on both the left
and the right sides.
So lets scroll up here.
And just below where
it says, text align center, we'll go ahead
and say, clear both,
save that out, switch back to the browser
and refresh.
And as you can see, the footer is now
exactly where it belongs again.
There's still those spacing problems up at
the top of the page, but we'll fix
that up soon when we put the finishing
touches on our navigation and header.
Our gallery is pretty much done, we'll
need to do some additional work to make
it look better on desktop browsers and
we'll also need to do some mobile testing,
but so far things are coming together.
We're going to build out our navigation in
just
a moment, but first, let's take a quick
code challenge.