We've coded up our HTML, reset the CSS,
added foundational styles, some colors,
and some typography.
I mentioned this earlier.
But so far we've only been building the
styles for the mobile version of our site.
Now we're ready to start getting into more
intermediate techniques.
Let's get started by building out our
image gallery.
First, I want to review our HTML.
We built our gallery
as an unordered list.
Here, we have the unordered list
container with list items inside of it.
Each list
item is composed of a link and inside of
that link is
a image and its caption, there are
multiple
unordered lists on our page so let's add
an id to this list so
we can identify this list in particular.
I'll call it gallery.
Great.
Now, let's jump into our CSS after saving
this file,
and let's start building out the styles
for our gallery.
This particular gallery is going to take
up two columns on our mobile site.
Later on, we'll expand it to three columns
on the desktop layout.
But most of the styling we'll need will
already be complete by that point.
We'll select the gallery element in a
moment.
But first we need to add some special
styling to our images on our site.
I'm going to tear off this tab in Google
Chrome,
and expand it so that we can re-size this
browser window.
Now, presently, this is what our site
looks like
when we re-size it so that it's closer to
a mobile size.
You'll see that we have some positioning
issues,
but most importantly, our images are
entirely too large.
So, that's what we need to fix right now.
I'm going to leave the browser window like
this, because that's the way that
we should be looking at it, if we're
building out the mobile version first.
In order to fix our images, we're going to
give them a max
width of 100% in the general section of
our CSS.
So just like this.
I'll go right below the anchor element
styles, and I'll type image,
and say, max width 100%.
This won't generate any immediately
obvious changes, but it will become
important once we start resizing the list
items, which contain our images.
Basically, this max width of 100% tells
the
images to fill the width of their parent
container.
If the container shrinks down in size,
then the image will shrink down with it.
Without this piece of styling, the images
would break outside
their containers, and we'd get some very
strange looking pages.
Let's style the gallery, so you can see
how this helps.
I'm going to create a new section of our
CSS called Page Portfolio.
That way we'll know
that this styling is specific to this page
and doesn't really get used on other
pages.
So, I'm going to copy our heading here and
I'm
going to scroll down and paste it just
below the footer.
And like I said previously, I'm going to
call this page
portfolio.
There we go.
And now, we'll select the gallery element
and apply some styling.
So we'll use the id selector, as we've
done previously.
We'll set the margin to zero.
Set the padding to zero.
And set the list style to none.
The new property here
is list style.
This will remove any kind of bullet points
from a list if we set it to none.
In this case, we're using an unordered
list to layout our gallery.
So, we don't want the bullet points.
Now, let's style the list items.
We want them to be in two columns somehow
and
there's many ways that we could do that in
CSS.
One technique
is to use a property called float, which
will make the elements appear side by
side.
I want you to follow along while I type
this.
Afterwards, I'll explain the code.
So, I'm going to select gallery and then
select the list items
inside of the gallery.
And we're going to say float left.
We'll give it a
width of 45%, a margin of
2.5%, a background color
of f5f5f5, and finally, a
color of bdc3c7.
There's a couple of things going on here.
First,
I'm going to save this and then refresh
the page
so that you can see what this code just
did.
As you can see, our gallery is starting to
take shape as a two column layout.
.
And, if we expand this out, it starts to
even look better at
desktop sizes but, there's still more
improvements
that we can do there, later on.
First, the big new idea here is the float
property, which is a property that allows
us to position
elements in a special way.
The idea comes from print design, where an
image is floated on the page,
to the left or the right, and the text
then flows around that image.
On the web, the float property has evolved
to become extremely versatile.
Floating these elements will make them
appear side by side, rather than stacking
on top of each other, like we saw
previously.
Second, I've set their width to 45%.
That means, regardless of the size of the
browser window, whether it's on a desktop
or a
mobile phone, each image will only ever
take up
45% of the total width of it's parent
element.
So, you can see here
how the images are scaling and, no matter
what size the browser window is,
those images take up 45% of the width.
Since
every parent element above the list items
are not set, they default to 100%.
That means that the width of our images
will
be 45% of the total width of the page.
45 divides
into 100 twice with a remainder of 10.
That means we'll have two images floated
side by side with
10% extra room that we can use to create
space between our images.
To create that space and round it up to
100%,
I've used the margin property and set it
to 2.5%.
So, if we go back to the browser window,
you can see that
each image has a margin on each side of
2.5%.
So, in other words, each image has a 5%
margin in total.
There's 2.5 here, 2.5
there.
And then the second image has 2.5 here and
2.5 there.
So if you take 2.5 and
multiply it by 1, 2, 3, 4 times.
That gives you a total of 10%.
That will fill the extra 10% of space that
we had to play with previously.
Finally, I've set the background color to
what will look like a medium gray color.
Let's flip back to our website.
If you look at our website, you'll
see that this background color comes
across for each one of the captions.
Finally, I've set the color of our text to
this gray color here.
You won't see that come across really,
unless
any of the captions are unlinked for some
reason.
Rather, what's being displayed
here is the color of linked text.
Which in this case is this green color.