Our navigation is finished, but now we
need
to create a structure for the image
gallery.
We'll do this with a similar technique
that also uses an HTML list.
Similar to our navigation area, we're now
going to use another
unordered list to build our gallery inside
of our section element.
So I am going to scroll down here and
delete this temporary paragraph
that's inside of our section, and instead,
I'm going to type an unordered list.
And inside of that unordered list, I'm
going to type a single list item.
We'll create other list items, but it's
easier to fill out this one first.
We'll then copy it and make the necessary
modifications because most
of these will be the same with just a few
small changes.
Now we need to pull in some images for our
gallery.
I'm actually going to pull in all the
images we'll need for the rest of this
project.
To download them, simply download the
project files associated with this video.
You should find a link to them next to the
video player.
Once you've downloaded them, you should
have a zip file that looks like this.
Next, unzip the file and then find the
folder inside called Image.
You can upload the files into Workspaces
by dragging them onto the Workspaces
sidebar.
To do this, simply select all of the files
inside the Image
folder and make sure that you don't select
the actual folder itself.
Then with just the files selected, drag
them into the Workspaces window
and drop them in the darkened area that
says, Drop Files to Upload.
This will automatically import all of the
files.
Now we need to create a folder inside of
our workspace called Image.
To do this simply right-click in any blank
area in the sidebar and select New Folder.
I'll type in img and hit Enter, and then
we need to drag each of our image files
into the folder.
So I'll drag all of these
into the folder here.
And the only file that should be outside
of the image folder is the index.html
file.
For the gallery images, you should feel
encouraged to use your own pictures.
You can, of course, use these but if you
want to customize
the site, you could use your own artwork
or your own photographs.
This project works best with images that
are sized to a width of
1,024 pixels, and a height of 768 pixels.
Or more commonly, 1,024 by 768.
We won't go into detail here about how to
resize images,
but most image editing programs like
Photoshop can do this very easily.
With our images in place, let's use them
in our layout like this.
I'm going to go to this list item and open
it up.
And inside, I'm going to type a tag called
img with an attribute called src.
Inside of that attribute I'm going to type
the value
img/numbers-01.jpg.
I'm going to type a second attribute,
called alt and
then I'm going to leave it blank for right
now.
Here, we've introduced the image element,
or img, for short.
Similar to some other elements we've
learned about, it's
self-closing, so, you don't need to create
a closing tag.
The image element has two required
attributes.
The first is the source, or src for short.
This is very similar to the href, or
hyperlink reference, that we learned about
for anchor elements.
It simply tells the browser where this
image file is located.
In our case, it's inside of the Image
folder and then we want to use the
file numbers-01.jpg.
This is what's called a relative path.
In other words, we're telling the browser
where
this image is located relative to our
index.html file.
The Image folder and the index.html file
are sitting at the
same level in our directory structure, or
our file tree.
Then inside of our Image folder, we have
our image.
This is different than an absolute URL.
For example, we can type http://.
[SOUND] The domain of our website, which
might be example.com, for example.
And then the path to our image.
However, instead of an absolute URL, we're
just going
to use a relative URL in this particular
case.
That will make it easier to upload our
site to a web server later on.
If that doesn't make sense to you right
now, don't worry.
We'll be using more examples of relative
URLs throughout this project.
The second required attribute is the Alt
attribute, which is short for alternate.
This is intended to provide a brief
description of the
visual for when the image isn't available
for some reason.
This might be because the site visitor is
actually
a search engine spider, which can't
actually see visual images.
It also could be because the site visitor
has images disabled in their browser.
Yet another reason is to assist site
visitors with visual impairments that use
special software
called a screen reader, which reads text
out loud to help them navigate the web.
In our case, we've left the Alt attribute
blank.
Because in just a moment, we're going to
add a caption to our image, just below it.
When you add a caption, having the same
text
repeated in the Alt attribute is typically
not necessary.
Let's save and then refresh our preview
quickly, to see what this looks like.
As you can see, we now have an image on
the page and it's very large.
But that's because we haven't applied any
visual styling yet.
We'll do that later on to help resize the
image.