[MUSIC]
The
most basic components of our site
structure are now in place.
Let's start filling in the details with
some navigation, content and more.
On most websites, you can click the site
logo on
the upper left corner to get back to the
homepage.
Right now we only have one page on our
site.
But soon, we'll have multiple pages that
will need to link together.
When a site visitor goes to another page,
this will be the link that takes them
home.
I'll type it out first and then, explain
it.
So I am going to, wrap our H1 and H2
elements, and an anchor element.
And we're just gonna type a little
attribute here.
And then we'll go ahead, and close it.
Just like that, and then more indent these
two lines here.
Links are created with what are called
anger elements or a tags.
The a in these two tags of course, stands
for anchor.
The anchor element gets its name because
it can be
used to anchor a URL to some text on a
page.
In this case, we're actually using the
anchor to go to another page.
Inside of the opening anchor tag, you'll
notice the HREF attribute.
This is short for hyper link reference.
Inside the quotes, I've stated that I want
the destination to be
our index dot html file, which is what
we're looking at right now.
When we have, other files to link, we'll
use other destinations.
Inside our header we're going to create
the navigation in the form of a list.
Which we'll style later.
The first part is easy.
We just have to add the nav element, which
is short for navigation.
So, I'm just going to skip down here, and
add in, our nav element.
You can use this element to wrap any
kind of website navigation that you put
together.
It doesn't have any special function
inside the browser.
And it doesn't add any buttons or other
visual bits, its
simply a semantic statement that says,
here's our navigation on the page.
Inside of the nav element we're going to
create an unordered link of lists like
this.
The UL element is short for unordered
list.
I say unordered because we could also
create an ordered list with an OL tag.
Until we add our own styling, this
unordered list will look like
a bulleted list, like you might create in
a word processing program.
An ordered list would look like a list of
numbers instead of bullet points like in
our unordered list.
Now, lets add some list items.
I'm going to open up our UL element here
and then I'm going to type a list item
element.
And I'm going to type the word, "
portfolio".
Then I'm gonna type another list item.
And type" about".
And then, one last list item, which will
say Contact.
Now, I've created three list item
elements, using these li tags.
Then inside I've added some text.
Let's save our work, and then switch over
to our preview, and refresh the page.
As you can see, our headline elements at
the top Are now colored blue with an
underline.
This is the default styling or a hyperlink
that's provided by the browser.
Our navigation looks like a bulleted list.
However, we need to add some links here,
in order for our
site visitors to get around to different
pages that we'll create later.
Let's go ahead and add those links right
now though.
So I'll switch back to my work space, and
in between
my opening list item tag, and the Word
portfolio, I'm going to type a hyperlink.
And I'm going to link this to index.html
because our portfolio
is actually going to be on our home page
or our index page.
And I need to wrap portfolio,
in a closing anchor, just like that.
Now, with my about page, I'm going to do
the same thing,
except this time, I'm going to choose a
different destination.
In this case, it will be about.
Dot html, and I'm just going to cut my,
closing
anchor tag there and put it around a bell,
finally,
I'm going to type contact.html for this
final destination here.
And I'm going to then close it.
So there we go.
We have three new links here.
Again, the first page is our Index page or
our Home page.
And the other two pages are our About page
and our Contact page.
These pages don't exist yet, but we'll
create them
once we're done with the HTML for our
first page.
Let's go ahead and save this.
Switch over to out preview and refresh,
and
as you can see, we now have hyperlinks.
For each one of our pages.
If you click on the links now, they'll
probably give you some type of error.
When a link doesn't work because the page
or content doesn't exist, it's called a
broken link.
And we certainly don't wanna launch our
site with any broken links.
We'll fix those later.