Let's wrap up this portion of the project
by building out the footer.
We already have our copyright in place,
but we should add some social links
and icons so that people can connect with
us from any page on the site.
First, let's add in the social icons for
Twitter and Facebook.
If you don't have a Twitter account or
a Facebook account or either one don't
worry.
You can go ahead and link to whatever site
you'd like
or you don't have to link to any site at
all.
If you do choose to link to another
website or another social network, just be
sure
to replace the imagery with the
appropriate logo
for that social network, or for that site.
The iconography we need for Twitter and
Facebook are included with the project
files for this video.
So if you haven't already downloaded the
images folder,
like we did in the previous video, be sure
to do that now and include them in the
project, simply by dragging them onto the
file tree here.
Now, let's go ahead and scroll down to our
footer.
And inside of this footer,
I'm going to type image src for source
and then I'm going to type the relative
path to our Twitter
wrap ping image here or PNG.
So I'm going to type
Twitter-wrap.png
and I need to go back to the beginning
here to make sure
that I include the image folder there
because it's inside of the images folder,
so just typing Twitter-wrap won't work.
You need the images folder.
And then I'm going to type an alt
attribute.
And in this case, we're not going to add
captions to these images.
So we do need to add an alt attribute.
So the alt attribute I'm going to type,
is just going to say, Twitter Logo,
because that's what this picture is.
Now to save some time, I'm going to copy
this line and paste it
because we just need to change Twitter to
say Facebook
and then we just need to change the alt
attribute to also say Facebook.
Again,
you could find alternative icons that you
like better provided
you have the permission from the owner to
use them.
Now, let's link these to our Twitter and
Facebook profiles.
I'm going to type in the links to my
personal Twitter and Facebook here.
But you should type in the links to your
own profile.
So, at the beginning of this line, I'm
going to type an anchor
element with the href.
Http://twitter.com/NickRP,
which is my username on Twitter.
Then I'm going to close this.
And I'm just gonna take this closing
anchor tag,
and put it at the end of this line.
So we have an opening anchor.
The image for Twitter, and then a closing
anchor.
So this will create a picture that links
to my Twitter profile.
Now, we need to do the same thing for
Facebook.
So I'm just going to copy that line and
paste it here.
We need to change
twitter.com to facebook.com.
And my username on Facebook is different
than my Twitter handle.
So I'm going to type Nick Pettit and then
at the end of this line, which
you'll notice has actually wrapped to the
next
line, I'm going to close my anchor
element.
If you don't want
to wrap to the next like this you can go
up to
the View menu and uncheck Word Wrap and
that will leave your lines
as is, but it will add in a scroll bar
down at the
bottom so that you can see what's at the
end of the line.
I actually prefer to keep word wrap on so
that I can see all of my code at
once without having to scroll
horizontally.
So again, even though this looks like it's
on a new line, it's actually all one line.
And you can see that if you look at
the line numbering over here on the left
hand side.
Now let's save the page, go to our
preview, and refresh.
If
I scroll all the way down to the bottom of
the page, you can see the logos for
Twitter and Facebook and if I click them,
it will bring up my Twitter profile.
Now there is one more very important thing
that
I'd like to point out before we wrap up.
We've used two different types of links on
this page now.
Notice how the links in the images
are relative links like we discussed
previously,
but over here, we have the full web
address, which is an absolute link.
A relative link describes the location of
a file relative to the current file.
So again, index is relative to the image
folder.
They're sitting at the same level in the
directory structure.
And you can see that because they're
aligned with one another just like so.
And then inside of the image folder,
is our image, twitter-wrap and
facebook-wrap.
If you can't see all of the filename, you
can go ahead and adjust the size of the
gutter here or the size of the file tree
relative to the size of the text editing
area.
As a general rule you want to use relative
links whenever possible,
because this will make your website more
portable.
What I mean by that, is when we take
our entire directory structure and put it
somewhere else,
all of these relative links will still
work with
this index file, because they're in the
same directory together.
If Iwere to type out the full domain name
here,
so we could say, example.com/image/ the
name
of the file, and if we did that, and then
we tried to put this website on
another domain, such as example two or
something like that,
then all of our images would break because
it's not the same path anymore.
So you want to keep
these relative.
However, because we're linking to an
external website such as Twitter
and Facebook in this particular case We do
need to use absolute links.
So to remember this rule just think you
need to use relative links whenever you
can and only use absolute links when you
absolutely have to.
We added a ton more markup to our page.
It can take a long time to memorize HTML
elements and CSS properties.
And even the best web designers look
things
up using a search engine all the time.
Don't worry if you're having trouble
taking in everything we're covering.
What will help more than anything else is
lots of practice so let's pause for
a code challenge and code some more with
the elements that we just learned about.