[MUSIC]
Great job making it this far.
We've created our homepage but now we're
ready
to build the About page and the Contact
page.
The About page is less complex than the
Contact page so,
let's start with that first and then build
on what we learn.
First we're going to create a new file
called about.html.
Unlike our index file, we can actually
call
this file, whatever we want.
As long as we maintain the .html
file extension.
So if I click on,
My Work Space here, using the right mouse
button, I can
select new file and I'll just go ahead and
type about.html.
And work spaces
will open the blank file for me.
Almost every web server recognizes the
special file name index.html.
And it will use it as the home page, which
is why we want to keep its special naming.
With our about.html file created, let's
copy all of the
HTML from our index page over to the about
page.
Because most of what we need is already
there.
The easiest way to select all of our text
is to use the keyboard shortcut
Cmd+A on a Mac or Ctrl+A on Windows.
So if I just click in my text editing area
and hit Cmd+A on my Mac.
And then hit Cmd+C to copy all of the
text.
I can then click on about.html and hit
Cmd+V to paste all of
it.
Now, let's save the file and see what it
looks like in the browser.
So, if I switch over to my browser here,
I can actually click on About and it will
take me to
about.html.
Of course, the page looks exactly the same
as our home page, index.html.
Because, we haven't changed
anything yet.
So let's start modifying about.html.
I'm going to scroll up to the top of the
file here.
And first, I'm going to change the
selected navigation item over to about.
So I'll remove the class selected from the
portfolio navigation item.
And I will add the class selected, to
about.
Next, I'm going to delete everything
inside of our section element here.
And I can just start the selection,
and then hold down Shift+Click to continue
the
selection down to where my cursor is.
And then I can just hit the Delete key.
This will leave us with our header, our
navigation and our footer.
And then, leave us with a blank
section that we can fill out later.
That's because we want our
header and footer to be same on every
page, with the exception
of the selected item.
So I saved about.html.
And let's switch over to the browser and
go to about.html.
And as you can see, we have our header and
our
footer and then the content area or the
section is blank.
You'll also notice, that the About
navigation
item is now the selected nav item.
If I go back to Portfolio, The portfolio
is the selected nav item.
So if we click back and forth between the
two pages, the site visitor can see
which page they're currently on, just by
looking at navigation.
Now, let's go back to our HTML.
Once we're done, we'll add a little bit of
CSS to make it all work.
Inside of a section, I'm going to add a
profile picture of myself.
Inside of the img folder here,
I have the file nick.jpg.
And that's a picture of me.
So let's go ahead and add it.
I'm going to say image src, for source and
then the path to our image.
Which is
image/nick.jpg.
For the alternate text,
I'm going to say, Photograph of Nick
Pettit
and then I'm going to add the class
profile photo.
And then I'll close the tag.
This image should already be included in
your images folder.
But, you should add your own profile
picture.
A square image that is around 200 pixels
in
both width and 200 pixels in height should
work best.
But you can go up and down in those values
and the design should still work okay.
Experiment
and see what works best.
Next after our image, I'm going to add a
third level headline.
That says: About.
Finally I'm going to add some paragraph
text about myself.
You should customize your own text so that
it's about you.
I'm going to say: Hi, I'm Nick Pettit.
This is my design portfolio
where I share all of my favorite work.
When I'm not
designing things, I enjoy exercising,
playing video games,
drinking good coffee, and more.
Of course,
your description can be longer or shorter
and you can put whatever you'd like.
Next I'm going to put another paragraph.
And in this paragraph,
I'm going to say, if you'd like
to follow me on Twitter, my user
name is @nickrp.
Now, it would be nice
if we could actually click on that user
name and go to my Twitter profile page.
And again, this should of course, be your
Twitter profile or whatever link that
you'd like.
So we've wrapped it in
an anchor element.
And I'm going to copy and paste the link
to my Twitter profile.
Just like that.
So now, if you click in the footer, you
can go to my Twitter profile.
Or you can go ahead and just click this
link in the text.
Now, let's refresh the page, after saving
of course.
And see what it looks like before we add
any CSS.
So there's the picture of me.
There is our About headline.
And then there is the paragraph text that
we wrote.
And you can see that @nickrp is linked to
my Twitter profile page.
Great.