We're done with our portfolio and About
pages.
Now we need to get to the Contact page.
Let's get started.
First, we'll start the same way we did
with our About page.
We'll need to create a new file, called
contact.html.
So I'll just right-click in my directory
structure here.
And I'll say contact.html,
for the file name.
And when I hit Enter, you can see that it
opens up contact.html.
Now, let's copy our HTML
from the About page, and paste it in.
To do that, I'm just
hitting Cmd+A on my Mac, or Ctrl+A if
you're on Windows.
Then I hit Cmd+C to copy, or Ctrl+C if
And then finally, Cmd+V, or Ctrl+C to
paste it in.
Next, we'll need to change the selected
nav item to contact.
So, I'll go ahead and cut, by
hitting Cmd+x on my Mac or Ctrl+x if
you're on Windows.
And then I'll paste it back in.
Being very careful to preserve the
space, between class and href there.
So
now, if I save out, and switch over to my
preview, and refresh, I can go to the
Contact page.
And the contact nav item, will be
selected.
However the Contact page looks exactly the
same as our About page because we haven't
made any modifications to it yet.
So let's go back to the Contact page.
And, similar to what we did previously,
we're
going to delete everything inside of our
section here.
Eventually, this page will be a two column
layout, but
in our mobile view, it will only be a
single
column with two sections.
So, we need to create a second section
here.
So I'll just copy my section and paste it,
and
now we have two for each one of our
columns.
Again, this will be two columns on our
desktop view but our
mobile view will just have them stacked.
Now, the first section is pretty easy.
I'm just going to add a
third level headline.
And I'm going to say, General Information,
and then I'm going to add a paragraph.
This paragraph text will describe the best
way to get in touch with me.
I'll say, I am not currently looking for
new design work, but
I am available for speaking gigs and
similar engagements.
If you have any questions, please don't
hesitate to contact me.
And of course, you want to go ahead
and customize this text to whatever you'd
like.
Let's add another paragraph just to give
it some separation.
And in this paragraph I'm going to say,
please only use phone contact for urgent
inquiries.
Otherwise, Twitter
and email are the best way to reach me.
Now the second section is going to start
off with a H 3 as well.
And inside we'll say Contact Details,
then I'm going to create an unordered list
that will include a few ways to contact
us.
On the unordered list, I'll add the class
contact info.
So let's create that unordered list.
And say class, contact-info.
And just
to remind you one more time, this will be
the first column, and this will the second
column, side by side in our desktop
layout.
But in our mobile layout they'll be
stacked.
So these contact details, in our mobile
layout, will appear just
below this general information, and we'll
see that in a moment.
Now let's fill out this unordered list.
Inside I want three items for
phone, email, and Twitter.
On each item, we'll use different
types of lengths, based on the method of
contact.
For phone, I'm going to add the class
phone to the list item.
We'll need these classes later on when
we're
adding icons next to them in our CSS.
Next I'm going to create a link with
a fake phone number that's just for the
purposes
of this example, but if you feel
comfortable doing
so, you can add your own phone number
here.
So I'm going to say, a href we'll fill in
href in just a moment.
Inside of the link, I'm going to
say 555-6425.
And inside
of the href, I can say tel, for telephone,
with the colon, and then I'll put the same
phone number, 555-6425.
And save
that out.
As you can see, this is a different type
of link than what we've ever used before.
We've added the special keyword tel for
telephone inside
of the href attribute followed by the
phone number.
On smart phones this will tell the browser
that it's a telephone number it can dial.
So if you bring up this website on your
smart phone browser,
you can actually tap on this link and it
will dial this phone number or
it will at least present a modal window
asking you if you'd like to dial the phone
number.
Next, let's add the email length.
I'm going to create a new list item, with
the class, Mail.
I'm going to create an anchor element,
with a blank href attribute we'll fill out
in a moment.
And I'm going to put in a fake email
address, nick@example.com.
And inside of the href attribute I'm going
to say
mail to, with a colon and then
Nick@example.com.
Similar to the phone
number, I've used the keyword mail to.
This will tell
the browser its an email address that the
use can send mail to.
Typically this will open the default email
client on the site visitors computer; such
as,
Outlook Express or Apple mail or whatever
the
default mail program is for that
particular user.
This is just an example email address, so
be sure to add your own email address
here.
Finally, let's add a Twitter link.
I'm going to create a new list item, with
the class Twitter.
And then,
I'm going to create an HREF attribute
inside of an anchor element, and type
@nickrp.
Now, I'm going to use a slightly
different Twitter address than we've used
previously.
It's going to say
HTTP://twitter.com/intent/tweet
with a question mark.
And then
screen_name=nickrp.
This Twitter link is a bit different than
the ones that we've used before, because
it allows the site visitor to immediately
start writing a tweet
to us, rather than leading to the Twitter
profile page.
Just be sure to replace the username with
your own user name instead.
Let's refresh the browser to see what this
looks like.
So here, I'm on the Contact page.
And I've refreshed the browser.
Here are our two third-level headlines.
Here are the two paragraphs that we've
added.
And finally, here's the unordered list
with Contact Details.
We have a telephone number, which if I
click
in a web browser, isn't actually going to
do anything.
But it will bring up a
prompt on Smart Phones, if a user taps
this.
And then nick@example.com will actually
bring up
my email, so I can compose a message.
In this case it will bring up gmail,
because that's my default email client.
And then finally, if we click on the
Twitter link we added
here, you'll see that it doesn't bring us
to the Twitter profile
page, rather it brings us to a page where
we can immediately, type a tweet.
I'm going to go back because, I don't have
any need to tweet to myself.
This looks good so far.
Now we're ready to add some additional
styling.